友よ　友よ　君の中に
悲しいほどの純粋さを見た
日の暮れた学者の片隅で
汗まみれの素振りをしてたな
友よ　友よ　君の中に
笑えるほどの情熱を見た
「俺には夢があるんだ」と
馬鹿でかい声で叫んでいたな
君の街に朝日が
昇ってきたとしたのならば
賑やかな街の中を
走り抜けていったじゃないか
君の街に夜更けが
やってきたのだとしたのならば
大通りを抜けたところの
河原で語ったな
そうだろ　友よ
友よ　友よ　君の中に
綺麗な真心をみた
大切な命を抱きしめながら
真剣な顔をしてるな
いつの日か　今よりも　強くなりたい
ただ一つの願い　胸に咲く炎
何もできなかった日に　胸の誓いは生まれた
決してもう逃げださないと　ただひたすら前を向くと
傷つき倒れ　また立ち上がる　諦めなど知らぬものに
春は何度でも
この先に何がある　見えなくていい
一途なまなざしが　炎を灯すよ
discalm
どうなされた
青鬼蜻蛉
あいつだ
逃げて ここは奴の縄張りよ
What's wrong?
本字幕由诸神字幕组（kamigami.org）制作，仅供交流学习，禁止用于任何商业用途
日听:东吾 king  翻译:念白白 poopy   校对:木落 时间轴:wcaster
I-It's them.
Run... This is their territory!
The Aooniyanma...
Shinnakamachi
Magistrate's
Office
Insect Magistrate...
蟲奉行様
津軽の剣術師範 月島源十郎を蟲奉行所の同心として招く件
（同心：江户时代幕府的官吏职名，"与力"下属的下级官员）
Regarding our request
that Tsukishima Genjuurou, the master Tsugaru
swordsman, join the Insect Magistrate's...
本人は動けぬ身であるとのことで
He can no longer move.
And thus, we've accepted his son,
Tsukishima Jinbei instead.
代わりに 子息の月島仁兵衛を迎えました
I hope he will
江戸の泰平に役立ってくれればよいのですが
contribute to the peace of Edo.
My Rival is Female Ninja,
Hibachi!
あれ ここは…
Where am I?
む 無涯さん
M-Mugai-san...
死ぬまで勝ち続ける強い武士になりますから
I'll be a strong samurai who keeps
winning until the day he dies!
Indeed.
なんて悪夢なの
What a terrible dream...
おはようございま～す
Good morning, Sun-sama!
お天道様 今日もよろしくお願いします
Today's going to be another great day!
月島仁兵衛
Tsukishima Jinbei...
あいつのせいだわ
It's his fault.
The weather's nice today.
今日もいいお天気
仁兵衛様 お勤め頑張ってくださいね
Jinbei-sama, good luck at your new job.
では 朝の修練素振り3000回 始め
Well, it's time for morning training.
Three thousand swings.
Begin!
Today, I finally start my job at
the Insect Magistrate's Office.
いよいよ 今日より蟲奉行所のお勤めが始まる
父上 見ていてください
Father, watch over me.
I, Tsukishima Jinbei,
will succeed in my duties and live up
この月島仁兵衛必ずや立派にお勤めを果たし
to the expectations of those in Edo and of
my fellow Insect Magistrate's members!
江戸の人々や蟲奉行所の仲間たちの期待に 応えてみせます
そして 無涯殿
And Mugai-dono...
助けていただいたご恩を返すため
To repay you for saving me...
And above all, to be more like you,
何より あなたに近づくため自分はもっと強くなります
I will become stronger!
Jeez.
ったく 朝から最悪だわ
What a horrible start to a day...
おはようございます 火鉢殿
Good morning, Hibachi-dono!
Time for the morning meeting.
朝礼の時間ですぞ
おぉ すみません着替え中でしたか
Oh, I'm sorry... Were you changing?
では 自分は先に行っております
I'll go on ahead, then.
You pervert!
この エロ助が
今回の新入りは朝から元気なこった
Guess the new kid's a morning person.
どうせ すぐいなくなっちゃうのに
He won't last long anyway...
Jinbei-kun,
仁兵衛君 傷のほうは平気かい
how are your injuries?
おかげさまで 万全です
I'm just fine, thanks to you!
よかった
I'm glad to hear it.
ん　おぉ 無涯殿　おはようございます
Oh, Mugai-dono...
Good morning!
む む む… 無涯さん
M-M-Mugai-san,
お おはようございます
g-good morning!
じゃあ 全員 揃ったことだし
Right, since everyone's here, let's start by
まずは仁兵衛君にここの勤めを説明するね
explaining to Jinbei-kun our work here.
Please!
はい
昨日のお勤めでわかったと思うけど
I think you learned this yesterday,
but Japan is filled with giant
bugs that eat humans.
実は この日本には人さえも食らう巨大蟲がいる
今より 100年前から跋扈し始めたんだ
They first appeared about a century ago.
なぜ出現したのか どのように どこから来たのかは
Why are they here?
How did it happen?
Where did they come from?
今も調査を進めている
We are still investigating.
では 自分が昔 出会ったのは…
Then, the thing I ran into all those years ago...
Was probably an insect.
おそらく蟲だろうね
However, Tsugaru, where you are from,
仁兵衛君の故郷の津軽
及び奥州方面は寒さが厳しいせいか
as well as the Oushuu region,
have very cold climates,
蟲は 生息していないはずなんだけどね
and are not thought to be infested.
そして 10年前 巨大蟲から江戸の人たちを守るため作られたのが
And ten years ago,
the Shinnakamachi Magistrate,
or the Insect Magistrate's Office,
この新中町奉行所
二つ名を 蟲奉行所というんだ
was created to protect Edo from them.
我々は蟲奉行様のもと　日々蟲退治をしている
We work for the Insect Magistrate,
fighting bugs every day.
ほう その蟲奉行様はどちらにいらっしゃるのです
And where is the Insect Magistrate?
ぜひともご挨拶をさせてください
I'd like to meet him!
その必要はないよ
That's unnecessary.
蟲奉行様は 人にお姿をお見せにならない
The Insect Magistrate does not
reveal himself to others.
No way a new kid could meet him.
新入りが会えるはずねえんだよ
私たちだって会ったことないんだから
Even we've never met him.
Really?
なんと
ということで仁兵衛君 わかったかな
Do you understand now, Jinbei-kun?
この江戸の泰平は キミの腕にかかってるんだよ
The peace of Edo rests on your shoulders.
そのようなお言葉をいただけるとは 武士冥利 ここに極まれり
Those are the finest words a
Samurai could hope to hear!
この月島仁兵衛　お上より賜ったこのお勤め必ず果たしてみせます
I, Tsukishima Jinbei, shall fulfill the duty
appointed to me by the Shogunate!
I will do my very best and I look forward
to working with each of you!
粉骨砕身で臨みますので
どうぞよろしくお願いいたします
同じ江戸を守る者として
As a fellow defender of Edo,
皆さんの期待に必ず応えてみせます
I shall do all I can to meet your expectations.
Expectations, huh?
期待ねぇ
T-Trouble, Matsunohara-sama!
た 大変です 松ノ原様
蟲が出現しました
An insect has been reported!
どこに
Where?
立川から西へ向かったようですが 詳しい足取りは…
It went west from Tachikawa,
but that's all we know.
よし 分かれて捜索しよう
All right, we'll split up and search.
諸君
Everyone!
おう
Right!
Oh, Jinbei-kun,
あ 仁兵衛君　キミはしばらく見学ね
you'll be sidelined for a while.
Huh?
戦わなくていいから
It's fine if you don't fight...
待ってください　戦うなとはなぜですか
Please wait!
Why can't I fight?
自分だって蟲奉行所同心の一人なんですよ
I'm a member of the Magistrate's Office, too!
W-Well...
そ それは…
そんなの あんたが弱いからに決まってんでしょうが
Clearly,
it's because you're weak.
まぐれでクモ１匹倒して浮かれてたかもしんねえけど
Maybe you thought you were special
'cause you got lucky and killed a spider,
兄ちゃんには ここにいる誰ひとり期待してねえんだわ
but no one here expects anything from you.
帰れる家があるなら帰ったほうがいい
If you have a home to return to,
you should leave.
む 無涯殿まで
M-Mugai-dono, not you, too...
Jinbei-kun,
仁兵衛君
この蟲奉行所ではこの１年の間に入った新人が
no newcomer to the Magistrate's Office
in the past year has lasted even ten days.
１０日もたたずに全員 このお勤めからいなくなってしまったんだよ
我々にはこれ以上人材探しをしている時間はない
We cannot waste time searching
for additional personnel.
Thus, for the next month, you are
forbidden to draw your blade.
よって仁兵衛君はこれより１か月 刀を抜くことを禁ずる
これは与力である僕の命令だよ
(与力：江户时代作为奉行、所司代、城代、大番头的部下，指挥同心并分掌、辅佐事务之职）
As your leader, that is my order.
お… お受けいたしました
Understood...
ああ なんでよりによってあんたと組まなきゃなんないのよ
Why did I have to team up with you?
なに考えてんのよ
What are you thinking about?
自分は無涯殿のことを考えています
I was thinking about Mugai-dono.
自分にとって無涯殿は夜空に輝くきら星
To me, he is a star, shining in the night sky!
憧れのお方なのです
He is the man I want to be.
So you want to be like him, too?
あんたも無涯さんに憧れてたんだ
も？
あんたもとは　どういうことです 火鉢殿
What do you mean by "too," Hibachi-dono?
別に
Nothing.
もしや 火鉢殿も自分と同じく無涯殿に憧れて…
Do you feel the same way about him that I do—
It's not the same!
同じじゃない
I've wanted to be like him
for a far, far longer time!
私のほうが ずっとずっと憧れてるんだから
What?
なんと 火鉢殿
What is Mugai-dono like?
無涯殿とはいったいどんなお方なのです
You don't know anything?
何も知らないの
教えてください
Tell me, please.
無涯さんはね とにかく他に類を見ない剣の遣い手よ
Mugai-san is...
a master of the blade like no other.
Yes!
はい その他には
What else?
さあねえ
Hmm...
One rumor says that before
the Insect Magistrate's,
蟲奉行所に来られる前
蟲狩っていう集団にいたって噂はあったけど
he worked for an organization
called the Insect Hunters.
蟲狩
Insect Hunters?
つわものぞろいの集団よ
A group of powerful warriors.
I've heard that they're sometimes
hired to take out the bugs,
依頼されて蟲退治してるって話もあるけど
but no one really knows.
実のところ よくわからないの
Those are just rumors, though.
でもまあ あくまで 噂は噂
そんなミステリアスなところも無涯さんの魅力ってことよ
And being so mysterious is just
another great thing about him!
はい さすが自分の憧れのお方
Right...
That's why I look up to him.
だから 私のほうが憧れてるんだってば
Well, I look up to him even more!
自分も負けません
We'll see about that!
あのね 無涯さんはほんとに強いのよ
Listen, he's really strong.
存じています
I know.
自分はなんといっても 命を助けられましたから
After all, he saved my life.
私だって 助けられたわよ
He saved my life, too!
えっ　 火鉢殿も…
He did?
なんと ぜひとも そのときのことをお聞かせください
What?
Please tell me about it!
へぇ 聞きたいんだ
You want to hear it?
はい
I do!
私はね １年前に里から出てきたの
A year ago, I left my village.
お里はどちらなのです
Where is your village?
伊賀と甲賀の境にある　忍の隠れ里よ
It's a hidden ninja village that
borders Iga and Koga.
ほう ということは伊賀流でもなく甲賀流でもなく
Oh, then you don't practice
Iga-style or Koga-style.
何流なのです
Which style do you use?
そ それは…
W-Well...
いいのよ 別に
It doesn't matter.
とにかく 私たちは爆弾を使った発破にかけては
Anyway!
We were known as the strongest ninjas
最強の忍術集団と言われていたわ
when it came to the use of explosives.
Were known?
言われていた
うん 昔はね 泰平の世になって忍者はいらなくなった
Yeah, a long time ago.
After the civil wars ended,
no one needed ninjas anymore.
私が小さいころには もうみんな普通の仕事をしていたわ
When I was young, everyone had
already taken normal jobs.
However,
でも 一族の頭領だったおじいちゃまだけは
my grandfather, the head of the clan,
山奥で修行を続けていたんだ
was the only one who continued to train.
Just come down to the village...
いいかげん じいちゃんも里におりてこいよ
いくら 腕磨いたってもう意味ないんだよ
Getting stronger is pointless now.
No one needs ninjas anymore.
いまどき 忍なんて…
帰れ
Leave!
帰れと言ってるじゃろう！
I said to leave.
火鉢… また じいちゃんとこ来たのか
Hibachi...
Visiting your grandfather again?
Yeah.
うん
ったく じいさん　孫には甘いよな
He's such a softy when it comes
to his granddaughter.
そこだけは 普通のじいさんだ
It's the one way he's like a normal old man.
はい おにぎり玉
Here, I made you an onigiri!
よくできたね 火鉢ちゃん
Well done, Hibachi-chan.
I loved my grandfather.
私は おじいちゃまが大好きだった
And that smile that was only for me.
私にだけ見せてくれる笑顔も
And the way he devoted his life to strength.
一生をかけて　強さを追い求める姿も
いつしか私も 強くなりたいと思うようになった
Before long, I decided I also wanted to be strong.
そして 数年前
And several years ago,
若い女忍者がいると聞きつけた小鳥さんがスカウトに来たの
Kotori-san heard about a young female ninja,
and came to recruit me.
おじいちゃま 私 やるよ
I'm gonna do it, Grandpa.
蟲奉行所のお勤めを受ける
I'm gonna go work for the
Insect Magistrate's Office.
If I do well there,
私が蟲奉行所で活躍したら
maybe people will start to study your style again.
おじいちゃまの流派も また世の中に広まるかも
ふざけるなっ
Impossible!
我が流派は男のもの　男のものじゃ
The clan style is a man's thing...
A man's thing!
継がせるために教えたつもりはない
I didn't teach you so that you'd carry it on!
Even so,
それでもね 私はおじいちゃまが一生をかけた流派を守りたかった
I wanted to preserve the style
my grandpa spent his life on.
だから 私は 蟲奉行所でお勤めすることにしたの
That's why I decided to join
the Insect Magistrate's Office.
And then came my first opponent...
そうして やってきた初めてのお勤めのとき…
Mugai-san saved my life!
私は 無涯さんに命を助けられた
その強さに一発だったわ
I fell in love with his strength.
江戸には本当に強い人がいるんだって　思い知ったの
I realized Edo has some truly strong people.
And someday, I want to be strong enough
いつか私は無涯さんに認められるくらい強くなって
to gain Mugai-san's acceptance and to repay him.
恩返しをしたい
それくらい腕を上げたら　きっと…
If I can be that strong, I'm sure...
何と　火鉢殿も自分と同じ
Wow, you're just like me...
自分は無涯殿に救われた時
When Mugai-dono saved me,
父の言葉を実感したのです
I saw the truth of my father's words!
後ろにいる人が不安に駆られぬよう
That a samurai can never lose,
to keep those behind him from being afraid.
武士は負けてはならないという言葉を
無涯殿には後ろにいる者の不安をかき消す 圧倒的な強さがあります
Mugai-dono's overwhelming strength
makes those behind him feel safe!
あの時自分は　無涯殿を目標に歩んでいくことを決めたのです
Then and there, I decided that
I would make him my goal.
That's the kind of guy he is, right?
無涯さんってそういう人だよね
あの人みたいになりたいって思わせてくれる
He makes you think you want to be like him.
はい
Right!
He's cool, isn't he?
かっこいいよね
はい
Yes.
素敵よね
He's wonderful, isn't he?
はい
Yes.
最高よね
He's the best, isn't he?
はい
Yes.
って　何で私があんたと無涯さんのことで盛り上がってんの
Wait, why am I discussing
Mugai-san with you, anyway?!
Don't get cocky.
いい気にならないでよね
火　火鉢殿
H-Hibachi-dono...
どうなされた
What's wrong?
あっ　あいつだ
I-It's them.
逃げて　ここはやつの縄張りよ
Run! This is their territory!
Whose?
やつ
Aooniyanma
Demon Dragonfly
青鬼蜻蛉
The Aooniyanma...
あいつはトンボの一種
It's a type of dragonfly.
オニヤンマと同じく　小川の近辺に強い縄張り意識を持っているわ
Like other dragonflies,
it claims a river area as its territory.
そして　黄昏飛翔といって 日が落ち涼しくなると
And when the sun falls and it gets cool,
獲物を噛み砕くため 大空を舞い始めるの
it takes flight, in search of prey.
おお　さすが火鉢殿　お詳しい
You know a lot about them, Hibachi-dono!
当然よ　だってこいつは私が始めてお勤めをした時と
Of course I do.
Because it's the
same insect I fought my first time!
同じ蟲だもの
なんと
What?
月島　あんたはその二人を遠くに非難させて
Tsukishima, get those two out of here.
し　しかし火鉢殿　一人では
B-But, Hibachi-dono, you can't fight alone...
あんた　刀抜いちゃいけないって言われたでしょう
Weren't you told not to draw your sword?
それに　いい機会だわ
And besides, this is the perfect chance.
今度は私一人で退治してみせる
This time, I'll defeat it on my own!
月島　早く
Tsukishima, hurry!
はい どうかご武運を
Right!
Good luck!
いくわよ　青鬼
Here I go, Aooni.
During that first fight,
最初のお勤めの時
all I could do was sit,
shaking, behind Mugai-san.
私は無涯さんの後ろで震えてるだけだった
今はもう違う
But I'm not like that anymore.
Hydrangea Blossoms!
紫陽花玉
私はもうあの頃の私じゃない
I'm not the same person I was then.
とどめよ　こいつを一人で退治して
This is it!
I'll defeat it on my own and I'll prove that!
それを証明する
Fine with me!
上等じゃない
火が…
The fire...
Oh, no!
しまった
M-Mugai-san...
無　無涯さん
ご無事ですか　火鉢殿
Are you all right, Hibachi-dono?
つ　月島
T-Tsukishima!
言われた通り　二人は非難させました
I got those two out of here, as ordered.
Let's go!
いきましょう
W-Wait...
ま　待ちなさいよ
私の獲物だってば　私がやる
It's my prey.
I'll kill it!
一人でやらなきゃいけない
I must do this myself.
強くなったことを証明すれば
If I can prove my strength,
Mugai-san will accept me.
無涯さんだって　私を認めてくれるはず
You stay back!
あんたは下がってて
I refuse!
断ります
このお勤めは己の強さを証明する場ではありません
This job is not the place to prove your strength.
I'm sure Mugai-dono would feel the same.
無涯殿もそうお思いのはず
火鉢殿だって　分かっているでしょ
You understand that, don't you, Hibachi-dono?
Because both of us
なぜなら　自分達は 無涯殿が純粋に戦う姿に憧れたのですから
were drawn to him by his pure fighting style.
I didn't want to hear that from you, but...
あんたに言われたくないけど
しょうがないわね
That's fine.
いくわよ　月島
Let's go, Tsukishima.
こんなやつさっさと退治する
We'll finish it off fast!
承知
Right!
Always be ready for a fight!
常住戦陣
Secret Technique: Thousand Bladed Flowers!
秘技　小太刀千花
火鉢殿　お湯加減いかがでしょうか
Hibachi-dono, how's the water?
Not hot enough.
ちょっと温い
はっ
Okay.
仁兵衛君　剣を抜いたのかい
Jinbei-kun, did you draw your sword?
自分は…
I...
いいえ　月島は抜いていません
No.
He did not.
Well, he didn't remove it from the sheath.
ま　鞘からは　ね
時に火鉢殿
By the way, Hibachi-dono...
What?
何？
発破の技　此度もお見事でございました
Your explosion techniques today were splendid.
What's the name of your style?
あれは何流の技なのですか
誰にも言わない
You won't tell anyone?
もちろんです
Of course not.
じゃ教えてあげる
Then, I'll tell you.
What did you say?
何と申された
だから言ってるでしょう
I told you!
Chinpou-Style...
Chinpou-Style?!
珍宝流
【咳… ちんぽ（う）在日文中是男性。。。那什么的俗称】
珍　珍宝流でございますか
D-Did you say Chinpou-Style?
こ　声が大きい
You're being too loud...
あっ　なんと
Wow.
この　エロすけが
You pervert!
ちょっとは仲良くなったかな
Perhaps they're getting along a bit better.
Next Time
To master the blade, you must use konjac.
剣術のコツは蒟蒻にあり
Konjac?
蒟蒻ですか
はい　早速特訓です
Yes!
I must start training.
Oharu-dono, please lend me
those two big konjac balls.
お春殿　その大きな蒟蒻球二つお貸しください
もう仁兵衛様
Oh, Jinbei-sama...
次回　蟲奉行
Next time, on Mushibugyou:
九十九斬り　恋川春菊
The Killer of 99, Koikawa Shungiku.
The Killer of 99, Koikawa Shungiku!